Romualdi, Serafino Papers 5459
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Serafino Romualdi Papers
1936-1968
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Romualdi, Serafino
5459
10.5 cubic feet
10.5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Consists of Romualdi's correspondence with organizations and individuals in Latin American and Caribbean countries, as well as clippings, reports, etc. concerning these countries; correspondence concerning Italian labor and politics and Italian emigration to Latin America; correspondence of Jay Lovestone, George Meany, Robert Alexander, Matthew Woll, Benjamin Stephansky, Arturo Jauregui, and Nelson A. Rockefeller regarding U.S. involvement in Latin America's politics and labor movement; correspondence relating to the American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), Vice-President Richard M. Nixon's Latin American trip (1958), and a speech by Meany entitled "Inter-American Trade Unionism"; correspondence with officers of international labor organizations; clippings and manuscripts, newspaper and trade-union articles written by and about Romualdi; correspondence regarding Romualdi's post-retirement activities as a labor consultant for U.S. enterprises, the publication of his memoirs, Presidents and Peons, and lecture work; manuscripts of Romualdi's lectures (published and unpublished) on inter-American labor-management relations and politics, AFL-CIO activities, and trade-union history; manuscript copies and drafts of Romualdi's memoirs, published as Presidents and Peons by Funk and Wagnalls, 1967; correspondence of Richard M. Nixon on Latin American labor relations; itineraries and clippings concerning Nixon's Latin American tours; correspondence of Jay Lovestone, Richard J. Alexander and Jauregui on Free Trade Union Committee (1951-1954); letters regarding AFL-CIO tours to Latin America (1950, 1956, and 1958); and condolence letters to Mimi Romualdi on Romualdi's death (1967) and several portraits and photographs of Romualdi.
2298525
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 30, 1978
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 13, 2019
Biographical / Historical
In 1928, Romualdi was editorial writer for the Italian Language Daily trade union Newspaper "Il Mundo", jointly owned by the Italian locals of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. In 1933, be joined the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union as a member of the Editorial and Publicity Departments.
In July 1941, Romualdi went to Argentina, Uruguay and Brazil, where as a representative of the Free Italy Committee he directed a campaign to enlist the Italian population in those countries to the side of the Allies. After Pearl Harbor, he joined the staff of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Nelson Rockefeller. Romualdi founded the Italian-American Committee for Democratic Education with headquarters in Montevideo, Uruguay. He also worked closely with the Committee for the Political Defense of the Continent, whose main objective was to counteract the activities of the Nazi and Fascist agents.
In 1943, Romualdi returned to Washington where where he worked in the labor division of the Coordinator's office, then headed by John Herling. He joined the Office of Strategic Services in May 1944, where he remained until April 1945, when he was assigned to make a survey of the effects of United States policy in Europe on the large European population in South America.
Romualdi resumed his work with the ILGWU in the fall of 1945, and was assigned by the American Federation of Labor to establish contacts with Latin American Labor with the view of promoting closer cooperation between the democratic trade unions of the two continents. In this capacity, he toured Central and South America several times; was a member of the AFL labor delegation that visited Argentina in January 1947 and was one of the AFL delegates to the conference at Lima, Peru (in January 1948) at which the Inter-American Confederation of Workers was organized. Later, in 1951, he played a leading role in the organizing the Inter-American Regional Organization of Workers (ORIT), of which he became Assistant Secretary and editor of its Inter-American Labor Bulletin.
In March 1948, Romualdi was appointed full time Latin American representative of the AFL. He was a member of the Joint AFL-CIO Commission that investigated labor conditions in the Central Zone in January 1949, and was a member of the US delegation to the conventions of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) held in Milan, in 1951; Vienna in (1955) and Tunis in 1957.
Romualdi attended ILO conferences either as a US labor delegate or Labor advisor: in Mexico City and Montreal in 1946; San Francisco in 1948; Montevideo in 1960 and Buenos Aires in 1961. In August 1957 he attended the Inter-American Economic Conference held in Buenos Aires as a labor advisor to the US delegation. He attended, also as an advisor, the Punta del Este Conference in August 1961, at which the Alliance for Progress was launched. Romualdi also attended various presidential inaugurations of Latin American countries, either as a representative or a personal guest.
After the 1955 merger of the AFL and the CIO, Romualdi was named Inter-American Representative of the new organization and Executive Secretary of the AFL-CIO Inter- American Affairs Committee. Shortly after the establishment of the American Institute for Free Labor Development in 1961, in which he played a leading role, Romualdi became its Executive Director. The institute, a non-profit organization supported by labor, business and government, trained selected young leaders from Latin American and Caribbean nations in trade union fundamentals, the democratic process, defense tactics against infiltration by totalitarians or racketeers and the role of unions in the community.
In September 1965, be retired from his posts with the AFL-CIO and the AIFLD to undertake consulting work and to complete his memoirs, entitled Presidents and Peons, which were published in 1967 by Funk and Wagnalls. Mr. Romualdi was married to the former Miriam Blecher Friedman. Each had a son by a previous marriage. Serafino Romualdi died in November 1967.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists chiefly of Romualdi's correspondence with political and labor figures from Latin America, North America and Italy. Consists primarily of correspondence between Romualdi as Latin American representatitve of the AFL-CIO and various Latin American, Italian and America labor and political figure. Romualdi's international interests and activities focused on the labor movements in Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Costa Rica, Cuba, Guatemala, Italy, Peru, Uruguay, and Venezuela. Includes correspondence with organizations and individuals in Latin American and Caribbean countries, as well as clippings, reports, etc. concerning these countries; correspondence concerning Italian labor and politics and Italian emigration to Latin America; correspondence of Jay Lovestone, George Meany, Robert Alexander, Matthew Woll, Benjamin Stephansky, Arturo Jauregui, and Nelson A. Rockefeller regarding U.S. involvement in Latin America's politics and labor movement; correspondence relating to the American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), Vice-President Richard M. Nixon's Latin American trip (1958), and a speech by Meany entitled "Inter-American Trade Unionism"; correspondence with officers of international labor organizations; clippings and manuscripts, newspaper and trade-union articles written by and about Romualdi; correspondence regarding Romualdi's post-retirement activities as a labor consultant for U.S. enterprises, the publication of his memoirs, Presidents and Peons, and lecture work; manuscripts of Romualdi's lectures (published and unpublished) on inter-American labor-management relations and politics, AFL-CIO activities, and trade-union history; manuscript copies and drafts of Romualdi's memoirs, published as Presidents and Peons by Funk and Wagnalls, 1967; correspondence of Richard M. Nixon on Latin American labor relations; itineraries and clippings concerning Nixon's Latin American tours; correspondence of Jay Lovestone, Richard J. Alexander and Jauregui on Free Trade Union Committee (1951-1954); letters regarding AFL-CIO tours to Latin America (1950, 1956, and 1958); and condolence letters to Mimi Romualdi on Romualdi's death (1967) and several portraits and photographs of Romualdi.
Latin American correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of country.
Correspondence in Italian, general correspondence, manuscripts and clippings arranged in chronological order.
Documents of international associations arranged alphabetically by association name.
Post-retirement correspondence arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Lectures arranged alphabetically by subject.
Typescript drafts unarranged.
Miscellaneous correspondence, files, and clippings arranged by form of document.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Communism -- Chile; Communism -- Italy; International labor activities.; Italians -- Argentina -- Political activity; Italians -- Cuba -- Political activity; Italians -- Latin America -- Political activity; Italians -- Uruguay -- Political activity; Labor unions and communism -- Italy; Labor unions and communism -- Latin America; Labor unions -- Latin America; Land reform -- Latin America; Pan-Americanism.; Peronism.; Labor unions -- Argentina; Labor unions -- Bolivia; Labor unions -- Brazil; Labor unions -- Chile; Labor unions -- Cuba; Labor unions -- Guatemala; Labor unions -- Peru; Labor unions -- Uruguay; Labor unions -- Venezuela; Working class -- Bahamas; Working class -- Belize; Working class -- Colombia; Working class -- Dominican Republic; Working class -- Ecuador; Working class -- El Salvador; Working class -- Guyana; Working class -- Haiti; Working class -- Honduras; Working class -- Jamaica; Working class -- Latin America; Working class -- Mexico; Working class -- Nicaragua; Working class -- Peru; Working class -- Puerto Rico; Working class -- Trinidad and Tobago; Working class -- Uruguay; Argentina -- Politics and government -- 1943-; Bolivia -- Politics and government -- 1938-1952; Bolivia -- Politics and government -- 1952-; Brazil -- Economic conditions -- 1945-; Chile -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1970; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1920-1970; Costa Rica -- Politics and government -- 1948-; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1933-1959; Cuba -- Politics and government -- Revolution, 1959; Guatemala -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Italy -- History -- Allied occupation, 1943-1947; Italy -- Politics and government -- 1945-1976; Peru -- Politics and government -- 1919-1968; United States -- Foreign relations -- Latin America; Acuna, Juan Antonio; Alexander, Robert J. (Robert Jackson), 1918-2010; Antonini, Luigi, 1888-1963; Ascoli, Max, 1898-1973; Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio, 1901-1973.; Betancourt, Romulo, 1908-1981; Borlaff, Otero; Brinkerhoff, Charles; Capello, Giovanni Battista; Ciccotti, Sigfrido; Colotuzzo, Alberto.; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982; Figueres Ferrer, Jose, 1906-1990; Frondizi, Arturo, 1908-1995; Genit, Jose; Gentilli, Vittorio; Goulart, Joa~o, 1918-1976; Green, William, 1870-1952; Haya de la Torre, Victor Raul, 1895-1979; Horne, Hermes; Ibanez, Bernardo; Jauregui, Arturo; Levitas, Sol M.; Lipsett, Alexander S.; Lovestone, Jay; Lupis, Giuseppe; Malve, Augusto; McLellan, A.C.; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Migone, Raul; Monge, Luis; Mujal, Eusebio; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Nunez, Benjamin, 1912-; Oldenbroek, Jacobus H. (Jacobus Hendrik), 1897-; Pastore, Giulio, 1902-1969; Perez Salinas; Pern, Juan Domingo, 1895-1974; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Rimini, Riccardo; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Romualdi, Serafino, 1900-1967; Sforza, Carlo, conte, 1872-1952; Stephansky, Benjamin; Sternback, David; Tarchiani, Alberto, 1885-1964; Villatoro, Ruben; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; AFL-CIO; American Federation of Labor; American Federation of Labor. International Labor Relations Committee; American Institute for Free Labor Development; Anaconda Copper Co.; Confederacion General del Trabajo de la Republica Argentina; Confederacion Interamericana de Trabajadores; Confederacion Latinoamericana de Sindicalistas Cristianos; Confederation of Rerum Novarum; Confederazione Italiana Sindicati Lavoratori; Cuban Confederation of Labor; Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; International Labour Office; International Labour Organisation; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Italia Libre (Buenos Aires); Italian American Labor Council of New York City; ORIT (Organization); True Temper Corporation; United Fruit Company
2298525
- Argentina, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Specific dates, languages other than English, copy number, any special formats, and any special notes.
- Argentina 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Correspondence includes letters about reorganizing Argentina's labor unions after fall of Peron; letters from Robert Alexander on situation there; letter expressing discontent of COASI with ORIT/ ICFTU; letter from David Sternback to Meany on the Internat
- Argentina 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes letters to Francisco Perez Leiros and Henry Hammond concerning his retirement from IADSC and correspondence with Joan Brunetti on the activities in Argentina, circa 1966.
- Argentina Reports (1943 - 1947) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes history of Argentine Labor Movement; report on AFL trip (US Labor Delegation) to Argentina in 1947; various correspondence relating to that trip which was to investigate the extent of government (Peron) control over CGT.
- Argentina Reports 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes Resolution on the closing of "La Prensa (newspaper); report of CGT re Latin American Workers Conference in Paraguay (1952); Romualdi's confidential report on that "Peronista" conference; notes for Jay Love-stone on the fall of Peron (Sept.'55); B
- Argentina, Speeches and Articles, 1946 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Romualdi, "Argentine Labor and Peron" (circa 1946); Romualdi address at Rutger's Labor Institute (June 1947) on U.S. Labor Delegation trip; "The fake union strike against "La Prensa 1951; Robert Alexander article "Reconstructing the Argentine Labor Moveme
- Argentina Clippings, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7-21)
  mostly January 1947; Arranged chronologically
- Bahamas - Trinidad, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Included report on Administrative meeting of Caribbean Area Division of ORIT(CADORIT) as well as a report of CADORIT's Third Biennial Conference in 1958.
- Bolivia Correspondence, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Correspondence includes Romualdi's notes on Bolivian Trade Union situation especially PIR and AFL support; correspondence with Bolivian Ambassador Victor Andrade concerning ORIT relations w/Bolivia; other correspondence w/Jose Figueres, Luis Gostkowski an
- Bolivia Reports, 1944-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes report on labor and political situation in Bolivia and on the distribution of funds provided by the American labor organizations for the Victims of CATAVI by Bernardo Ibanez (1944); report on Bolivian labor and political situation by Victor Paz
- Bolivia Clippings (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Brazil Correspondence, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes correspondence w/Deocleciano de Hollanda Caralcanti concerning the CIT meeting in San Francisco in 1948; Letter on Labor in Brazil after elections in 1955; Report of CIOSL/ORIT on political and labor situations in Brazil after Vargas suicide; Cor
- Brazil Reports and Lectures, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Report by Romualdi on visit to Brazil in 1946; Report of Arturo Jauregui's trip to Brazil in 1955; "The Communist Idea-Weapons" by Carlos Lacerda 196l; George Meany's address in Rio de Janero 1956, San Paulo (1956); Report by Robert Alexander on Brazil's
- Brazil Clippings, 1951-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- British Guiana, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Correspondence w/Peter Grace re Pres. Jagan's anti-labor views
- British Honduras (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Includes letter from Harry Pollack to George Frazer concerning Nicholas Pellard; Harry Pollack's report to trip to Honduras; Romualdi's report on trip to Honduras; Excerpt from Latin American Report Newsletter concerning allegations that President Price i
- Chile Ibanez Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondence deal mainly with travel itineraries and contact between Romualdi and Ibanez, as well as denouncement of exiled Dominican Republicans against Trujillo. There are also letters concerning the situation in Chile; the inflation, 1952 elections,
- Chile Correspondence, 1946-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Romualdi memo concerning his meeting with Ibanez and other leaders of the Confederation of Labor concerning attempts to defeat the Communists; correspondence with Manuel Scone concerning U.S.'s apparent support of military junta (1949) and situation in Ch
- Chile Reports and Statements, 1946-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Includes report of the sentence against Ibanez (Secretary Gen. of CTCH) 1946; agreement on Trade Union Cooperative (ORIT - Chilean Con-federation of Copper Workers. 1951); report by Monge on situation in Chile between democratic trade union movement and c
- Chile Clippings, 1953-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Columbia, 1946-1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Correspondence includes cable to Matthew Woll of AFL concerning non-communist delegates walking out at 8th convention of Columbian Confederation of Labor; letter concerning Juan C. Lang's (Columbian Labor Leader) visit to U.S. (1946); 1947 report by SB on
- Costa Rica Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes memo to M. Woll concerning Reverend Nunez subsidy of Confederation of "Rerum Novarum" of Costa Rica; Corres. with Luis Monge dealing with the Communist vs. Rerum Novarum labor movements; and State Department intervention in C.R.; correspondence.
- Costa Rica Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Corres. w/Luis Monge re situation in Costa Rica and his running for V. P. of CIT
- Costa Rica Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes correspondence. w/Luis Monge; Victor Riesel concerning Communist influence in labor movements in LA; correspondence. with Alex Cohen (labor attach in CR) requesting confidential information; and routine correspondence
- Costa Rica Correspondence, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Corres. w/Jose Figures and Karen Figures (Pres. of CR & wife); and Luis Monge re Romualdi's trip to Cuba in 1959; other correspondence includes correspondence. w/Leopoldo Pita (CCT) concerning the situation of Peruvian workers and politics centering arou
- Costa Rica - Reports, Releases and Statements (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Includes report on Costa Rica under the Figures Govt. (1954); News releases dealing with AFL's position on Costa Rica; letter from Figures to Robert Alexander concerning activities of the State Dept.; Figures letter to Senator Smathers concerning foreign
- Costa Rica Clippings (Box 3, Folder 6)
  [CUBA ~ SEE Box 4]
- Dominican Republic Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes correspondence. between Julio Ballster and Francisco Aguirre concerning Dominican Republic labor freedom; letter to George Meany from Dominican Republic Labor Movement in Exile (CODDE) concerning AFL's support; letter to Meany from Barrister def
- Dominican Republic Reports and Statements, 1950-1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Includes ICFTU's report on Trujillo's anti-labor regime; CTC's petition against Trujillo (1956); SR memo to Meany giving background information; Report on Trujillo and Monge(l957); SR notes on D.R.; report on ICFTU mission to D.R. (1957); other reports.
- Dominican Rep. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  clippings
- Ecuador Correspondence and Misc. Doc., 1947-1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Romualdi memo to Woll (1947) concerning AFL aid to Confederation of Labor of Ecuador; Corres. w/Serge Barka Romero concerning Ecuadorian labor situation and communist influence (1950); Romero letter to AFL denying communist influence in Ecuador labor mov
- Guatemala, 1950-1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Includes correspondence with and concerning Ruben Villatoro and financial aid from AFL for the labor movement. (1954); Confidential memo concerning United Fruit Company and Labor in Guatemala (1955); Correspondence concerning and reporting the details of
- Guatemala Corres., 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Several periodic reports to Romualdi from Andrew McLellan on the political situation in Guatemala and El Salvador (1957-58); Letters to Arturo Jauregui from McLellan concerning its delegation; Francisco Monzon (Secretary. of Consejo Judicial de Guatemala)
- Guatemala Reports and Statements, 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Include "Labor in Guatemala" 1947; Interview with President Arevalo (1950) by Samuel Inman on Guatemala's position vis a vis the U.S.; Report and Recommendations on Guat. by SR(l954);Confidential report of Arturo Jaurequi on labor movement in Guat. (1953)
- Guatemala Reports and Statements, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Romualdi report on Guatemala (1956); McLellan report (1956) on the Trade Union Mov't. in Guatemala as well as a series of reports on Trade Unions in Guatemala by McLelland; reprint from Palabra Radical concerning ORIT visit(1956
- Guatemala Reports and Statements, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Includes a series of reports 1957-58 by A. McLellan concerning Guat. Labor Situation; Notes on ORIT Secretariat Meeting (1957) concerning Guatemala - ORIT AND CSG; "Trade Union Situation in Guat." (1957);"Guatemala Rebuilds on Democratic Foundations" by S
- Guatemala Clippings, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Correspondence dealing mainly with the influence of the Communists in the CTC in Cuba, (affiliated with the CTAL) and also the relationship of the CTC in the Lima Conference where the Confederacion Interamericana de Trabajadores (CIT) was formed. Corres
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Correspondence concerned mainly with Cuban political situation (Batista Coup) and the effect on the CTC and its relationship to the free labor movement. Correspondents include: Julian Gorkin, Mario Hirigoyen, Angel Miolan, Jay Lovestone, George Meany.
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Correspondence concerning the CTC under Batista's dictatorship. One letter, from CTC leaders in exile, outlines the history of the CTC and the effect of the Batista Coup, along with the mounting revolution tinder Castro. These leaders censure the CTC Pres
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Correspondence centers around the ORIT revolution re Cuban situation under Batista with Castro Revolution threatening, Mujal and CTC leadership vehemently protest the labeling of the CTC as a Communist and anti-democratic regime. Some correspondence deal
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  Contains personal correspondence as well as letters discussing the Cuban situation after Batista's fall. Reports from inside Cuba and letters of intent from the supporters of Castro's Revolution. Includes a declaration of the principles of the "Labor, Hum
- Cuba - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)